INSPIRED BY TRUE EVENTS
BARCELONA, FEBRUARY OF 1976
THREE MONTHS AFTER
FRANCO'S DEATH
Okay, let's go.
Step down.
This way.
- Move it.
- Stay calm.
PRISON 77
Are you okay?
Have you got a cigarette?
What's your name?
And a light?
Juan.
But everyone calls me Ruby.
How old are you, Ruby?
Sixteen.
- Get up!
- Okay, Juan Vicente Lopez.
Out.
Juan Vicente Lopez.
- Who's Juan Vicente Lépez?
- That's me.
Are you deaf?
I said are you deaf!
Answer me when I talk to you,
damn it!
He's just a kid.
You shut up.
A kid now.
In a year, a son of a bitch.
Like all the rest.
This way.
Move!
- Back again?
- What can I say?
- The place grows on me.
- How long did you last this time?
One week, my record.
- Bend over and get up.
- Turn around.
- What did you do this time?
- Nothing.
- Social hazard.
- Open your mouth.
- You should find a job.
- Look at me.
Would you give me a job?
Democracy will.
My ass, it will...
Contagious diseases?
Flex.
Lice?
Democrat.
- Not checking my head?
- I said not to call me that.
I won't go near you, you bastard.
Turn around and flex.
Spread your legs.
Good evening, Domingo, sir.
Get dressed. You too.
I'll give you 250 pesetas
for the suit.
It's not for sale.
Get up.
Listen. Mr. Domingo is right.
Sell it to him or they'll take it
from you inside, and for free.
Get dressed. You're going
into sanitary period.
Two weeks of isolation to make sure
there's nothing contagious.
Take your blanket and mattress.
Not the mattress.
That's 250 pesetas.
- I don't have any money.
- No mattress.
Take the bucket. And don't spill it,
that's your water until tomorrow.
I don't want to eat,
I want to take a shower.
- What for?
- I've been here for three days.
My body is covered with weals.
- There are bugs.
- Kill them.
I smell bad.
Use the bucket.
No showers in sanitary period.
Why not?
It says so in the rule book.
I want to see the rule book.
You want to see the rule book?
- Do you really?
- Step aside, Ramén.
Coming through.
Are you hungry?
You look familiar.
La Ladera, right?
The ghetto by Montjuic.
- You're mistaken.
- No way.
I have a good memory.
You need a plate.
Want anything?
I can get you
anything but a woman
or a helicopter. Just ask.
Knock it off, Blacky.
- We're in a hurry.
- Coming, Ramén.
Do you smoke?
- I don't have any money.
- Pay me when you can.
I trust you, we're neighbors.
There's no hurry.
And cheer up.
You can tell it's chicken.
It has a leg.
JUMP TO COLOR
When do I get out?
You're preventive,
not until the trial.
- When is the trial?
- I don't know.
- Can it take long?
Approximately?
I don't know.
You stole
nearly one million pesetas.
What?
How much did you say?
997 thousand.
Look, it's right here.
That's not right.
I only took 50 thousand.
A salary advance.
- The rest wasn't me.
- According to this,
you convinced your friend,
the Head of Accounting.
Who?
Miguel Ferran Requesens.
He signed the complaint,
along with his father,
- the company owner.
- That's a lie.
It was his idea, he proposed it.
Well, he has half the company
as witnesses saying the opposite.
And they all say you were
spending beyond your means.
Of course they say that.
He's the owner's son.
And you aren't.
How much time are we talking about?
Between six and eight years.
I am not a criminal.
I can't get six years for that,
it makes no sense.
You can hire a private lawyer
if you want. I have to go.
I have to see five more this morning
and they're all just
as innocent as you.
I'll let you know if I hear anything
about the trial.
I want to shower!
I want to take a shower!
I am not a criminal!
I'm Manuel Merino, the warden.
I was told you want to see me.
I won't eat.
Not today, tomorrow or ever.
I won't eat that
until I can take a shower.
And I want to file a complaint
with the Penitentiary Department.
I've been like this for over a week.
With no idea when I'm getting out
and sleeping on this.
Washing and drinking from a bucket
like an animal.
Why doesn't this man
have a mattress?
Bring him paper and a pencil
for the complaint.
And let him shower.
It's on the house.
They asked me to give you this.
HANG IN THERE, YOU'RE NOT ALONE.
I'm leaving tomorrow,
I'm leaving tomorrow.
Great, Juanito,
- What time?
- Tomorrow.
I'm leaving tomorrow.
In back, third block.
After you.
Come in, he doesn't bite.
And you, get up.
Where are your manners?
Pino.
Manuel.
Your suitcase?
This is your bed.
Or should he sleep with you, Pino?
Listen to me, Manuel.
I'm fine with Blacky renting you
his side because you're neighbors.
- Show him the shirts, Pino.
- But this is my cell.
And in here what I say goes.
Understood?
Understood.
I know you made trouble in sanitary.
But not in here,
with inmates or blisters.
Blisters are guards.
This is my side.
When the blanket is closed,
it's closed.
You knock, I answer,
if I say yes you come in,
otherwise I'm not home.
Or not in the fucking mood.
Can you read?
Sure, he can.
Look at his jacket.
Don't touch the novels.
They're all the same.
Spaceships,
the future, stuff like that...
You need to shit,
ask Blacky for paper.
Not with the novels.
And if you want to read one,
you rent it like everyone else.
20 pesetas per novel.
And you see the shirts?
Finally the shirts.
Go near one, even breathe on one,
- I'll cut off your balls.
- Breathe on one, he says.
He's a dandy.
You know what that is, right?
Understood?
Understood.
Want some?
Good.
Clean this up.
- Hi.
- Damian!
Come here right now.
This kid is too big.
Are you sure he's mine?
Of course he is.
And you, Maribel,
how are you?
Have you got a boyfriend?
Little guy, do you miss your dad?
What about me?
- Run along with Auntie Carmen.
- Goodbye!
And your sister?
- Outside.
- Why doesn't she come inside?
- She's not well.
- What?
Lucia, talk louder, please.
She's not well. She says she doesn't
want to see you like this.
She doesn't understand
why you stole that money.
I'm not a thief, Lucia, believe me.
Tell your sister.
You have dark circles
and your face is swollen.
You're getting a boil.
How long will you be here?
- I don't know.
- Finish up!
One year? Two?
- I don't know.
- That's it, let's go!
Please, talk to your sister.
Tell her to come and see me.
She's all I've got.
Hey! Let me go!
- Help!
- Easy, Sandokan.
Why are you in your underwear?
Get dressed!
I want to file a complaint
with prison management.
- What's the problem?
- I was just robbed in the yard.
Four inmates.
There were also two guards
and they did nothing.
They probably didn't see.
That's 300 pesetas.
The stamps for the complaint form.
That's the price of democracy.
Have you got the money?
No.
Then no democracy.
Take it easy.
Come with me.
I can give you clothes.
Hey!
You're not alone.
Thank you.
- I'm Boni.
- Manuel.
- I can't pay for the clothes.
- You don't have to.
We have a fund for inmates.
You have a gumboil.
My tooth really hurts.
Let me see you.
I'm a doctor. The prison doctor
isn't here. He never is.
Have a seat, go on.
It's morphine for the pain.
I have to cut and drain it.
Hold still.
Come in.
Andrés, look outside.
This is Agustin,
he manages workshop.
Martin Puente, from the union.
- He just came from Madrid.
- You're not the only one
who thinks prisoners have rights.
- But you have to demand them.
- Even if no one dares.
- How long have you been here?
- Three weeks.
Open up.
Does this hurt?
You've seen what's here.
Poor and illiterate men,
no real lawyers
and judged by fascist courts.
Now don't move.
It's just one second.
That's it.
Lots of immigrants. Andalusians,
Extremadurans,
most of them for being jobless,
petty theft
or their political ideas.
Or sexual condition. Hold that.
The law of rogues and vagabonds.
You know it, right?
Everything Franco doesn't want
on the street is in here,
under the rug.
Out of the way.
You can read, right?
This is from Carabanchel.
The initials mean:
"Prisoner Rights Association."
It's like a union for inmates.
They're organizing
to request amnesty.
- A pardon.
- A general pardon.
If the country's starting over,
so can we. We have the same right.
What do you want me to do?
Tell people.
Very carefully.
The whole prison should know.
We have to be united.
I don't want any more trouble.
- Afternoon.
- What are you doing out here?
I'm leaving.
- What are you doing?
- I'm treating him.
Them too? Or are they nurses?
Everybody out.
Let's go.
Head for the yard.
Antibiotics.
- Five days.
- Thank you.
Only one, see him?
Anarchist.
Several together in a group
arguing...
Socialists.
This guy with the book...
Communist.
- You don't get along?
- Not an issue.
The political ones
keep to themselves.
- Where are you going?
- That's my suit.
Forget about it.
- Who is he?
- Marbella. He runs the 6th.
And Horoscope, his psychic.
The Brazilian.
Pelé's first cousin.
I know the kid.
What's he doing here?
They run away from the reformatory.
What does he do with him?
Favors in exchange for money.
Nothing good.
That's what you get in the 6th.
The worst.
Open up, it's Blacky!
I'm coming!
- What's up, Blacky?
- I need work, Agustin.
Maribel's communion is next month.
Her third communion
in two months.
She's a huge believer in God.
I'll call you
when the shift is over.
What do you do in workshop?
A day in workshop
is one day less in jail.
Well, and they pay us,
even if it's peanuts.
In here you get by on very little,
everybody's poor.
Why are you here?
Never ask that. It's impolite.
Stealing, why do you think.
Like almost everybody here.
How many years?
Half screwed.
- And him?
- Who, Pino?
If I'm half screwed, he's screwed
all the way. For life.
They say he killed two
in a robbery and a cop.
- They say.
- Depends on the day.
Some days two, others nobody.
True or not,
nobody messes with Pino.
Not even that bastard Domingo.
There must be a reason.
I also hear he has cash
stashed away here in the prison
from a heist or something.
Blacky.
Listen, Agustin.
This is my friend Manuel.
He just came, he needs work.
See if you can fit him in.
I have someone down next week.
Come by.
You can learn
to stitch soccer balls.
That will be a huge help in life.
Time to put the country to work.
Stick around.
I'm leaving tomorrow.
How did you get in?
The local priest signed a paper.
It says I'm your girlfriend.
You asked him for it?
Your sister isn't coming, is she?
No.
Could you please leave me alone?
I'd rather stay.
The bus doesn't leave until 7.
I have nothing else to do.
I asked around.
You could be here a long time.
Up to four years without a trial.
Asked who?
I can come and see you.
Bring you things.
If it's not too expensive.
I'm studying.
I know you're lonely.
If I don't come, nobody will.
You don't have to come
and see me, Lucia.
I don't need it.
I'm done.
Amnesty! Amnesty!
You've never ridden an elevator
in your life.
- So what?
- What do you mean, so what?
Riding is one thing,
installing is another.
This country is growing, Pino.
Not outwards like you, upwards.
- What's so funny?
- Do you really think
they'll let you and me go?
Why not? And this guy too.
It's a new country, Pino.
The old laws are no good anymore.
And we're here because of them.
- It's over.
- What's over?
They've given amnesty before,
and here we are.
Know what your problem is?
What's my problem?
You're a pessimist.
Yeah, yeah, don't laugh.
You're an orphan,
that's why you're a pessimist.
At least I don't have
a dead man's shoes.
What dead man?
I'll wear these when I'm a free man.
You bought those shoes
from the guy in the infirmary.
Yeah, right.
That's how I know they're the shoes
of a dead man.
Not today, Pino.
Do it again.
The bottle.
I saw you wipe it.
It's the second time
you've done it.
Do I disgust you?
Answer me, damn it.
Sooner or later you'll be
just like me, you got that?
The same.
Don't point at me.
- Okay.
- Just a matter of time.
That's what jail is for.
- Tourist, you're a tourist.
- Don't point at me.
Okay, that's enough.
Well?
Like new. Look.
Check out Blacky walking down
the street. Look.
"Bye, Blacky." "Bye, Antonio."
"Damn, you bought a new car, eh?"
"Yeah."
"They let you out?"
"Amnesty, Antonio."
"Look at those pretty shoes."”
"You see that?"
"Pretty, huh?"
I heard you were looking for me.
Yeah, sit there
and let me have a look.
Let's see how your mouth is doing.
Open up.
Remember the flyers we showed you
the other day?
We need people to write them.
Almost nobody can write.
Raise your head.
What's going on?
The amnesty. Only the political
prisoners are getting out.
Put this away.
That looks much better.
Write with your left hand so they
can't recognize your handwriting.
Rodriguez Fuentes, Diego,
downstairs with everything.
Gomez Méndez, José,
What are you doing?
Counting how old my kids will be
when I get out.
I'm not good with numbers.
And the bastard is always right.
I don't know how he does it,
but he's never wrong.
Arévalo Rochas, Pedro Pablo,
downstairs with everything.
He should pick lottery numbers.
Puente Lopez, Martin,
downstairs with everything.
Arévalo Rochas...
Don't forget the rest of us!
Silence.
Gonzalez Espicia, Alfonso,
downstairs with everything.
What's up, Blacky?
57.
I'll be 57 years old
when I get out of here, Manuel.
An old man.
I know you're awake, Pino.
Read me something
to help me fall asleep.
"At 23:00 hours,
Capricorn Colony time,
I left the base
to return to the ship.
The red night predicted
a difficult voyage.
No human came to say goodbye.
I crossed the platform
and entered the capsule.
The iridium thrusters ignited.
And suddenly... time stopped.”
NOVEMBER 1976
Get up!
- Let's go!
- What's going on?
- Let's go.
- What's happening?
- Move it.
- What is it, Ramon?
You're hurting me!
Where are you taking me?
- Ramon!
- Let's go.
What's the problem, Ramon?
A tunnel in the kitchen.
They're questioning him.
We think he and his friend
Emilio Simon are involved.
He's not his friend.
What happened?
Okay, okay.
What's going on, Ramén?
Keep moving.
Stop! Ramon!
What are you doing?
Fuck!
Emilio Simon.
- Do you know him?
- A jinx.
- Let's go.
- Coming for me again?
Nobody else?
And the other guy?
The other guy is Blanes, the Miner.
Good at breaking out,
bad taste in friends.
Did you know about the tunnel?
All prisoners
have the right to escape.
He won't be 57
when he gets out anymore.
Inside.
Go on, he'll be back in no time.
Lunch!
The prison has decided today
only workshop prisoners
will leave the block.
To compensate, we'll leave
your cells open at siesta time
and there will be fried eggs
for dinner.
Where is Blacky?
Blacky is dead, Pino.
What do you mean? Dead, how?
A heart attack
during the interrogation.
I'm very sorry. Gather his things.
I want to give them to his wife.
I don't know how you can eat, Pino.
What, you don't care?
You don't care about anyone?
They beat him to death!
It was them!
Nobody move!
They killed Blacky!
Murderers!
Everybody sit down!
Nobody move!
Here they come!
Get up!
Back to your cells!
If you don't want trouble, leave.
Amnesty!
They treat us like animals!
Amnesty, freedom!
Amnesty!
Freedom!
Let go of me!
Get up. You have a visitor.
There can't be two of you,
only one.
I'll stay.
Please, step back. I have to speak
to my client alone.
And I have to watch you.
Name and badge number, please.
Half an hour.
Not one minute more.
I think you got the wrong prisoner.
I already have a lawyer.
Court-appointed, I know.
Manuel Gomez Garcia, right?
I'm Arnau Solsona. I represent
the March 17th Attorney Group.
- I can't pay you.
- I'm not here for money.
We read the flyers.
And we want a new country too,
outside and in prison.
Your court-appointed lawyer
won't get you out of here.
And you will?
At least we'll try.
For now,
I'm getting you out of isolation.
You can't be in there any longer,
it's not legal.
And I'll try to get
your trial moved up.
This here is only a complaint.
That doesn't necessarily
mean it's true.
As you know, the government
has released political prisoners
but they've forgotten us.
That's why we started
the Prisoner Rights Association
like in other prisons
like Carabanchel or El Puerto.
All of us here today
are with the PRA
and we have the support
of the attorney group.
Which had never happened.
But if we want amnesty,
we have to make our voices heard.
Andrés.
People don't know
what it's like in here.
If they knew, things would change.
How do we let them know?
- Get the press in here.
- How do we do that?
Not even a newspaper.
We know what you would use it for,
Julian.
Shut up.
They could throw a camera
over the wall.
- That's right.
- Luis.
- I vote for a hunger strike.
- Not food, for God's sake.
- Hunger put most of us in here.
- With the shit they give us.
With what I can eat.
You'd rather suck, right?
Please.
Walk.
Wait outside, keep watch.
Good afternoon.
That PRA thing.
The progressive lawyers,
isn't that the PRA?
I want you to sign me up
and the whole 6th block.
I want them to defend us too.
We're working, Marbella.
You can't be here.
He's not in workshop.
Or him.
Or you.
What's the problem?
We aren't prisoners in the 6th?
Fucking great.
Manuel Gomez.
ANSWER ME OR I'll COME SEE YOU.
I KNOW WHERE YOU ARE.
SO YOU DON'T MISS ANYTHING.
THE FUTURE WILL BE HERE
VERY SOON.
I just saw the lawyer lady
you sent me.
It's the first time in my life
someone read my whole file.
She knows more about me
than I do.
I'm glad.
Me too.
Want some?
That meeting you all had today...
What meeting?
The secret meeting in workshop.
Some of them were not the type
you're looking for.
- What type are they?
- Bonnies. Queers.
Wackies. Flounders.
Snitches.
Next time ask
before sending me to anyone.
What are you doing?
Are you crazy?
You want them to take you too?
- Do you recognize him?
- No.
Do you?
Roll call.
And Agustin?
Did you knock?
Why isn't he coming out?
It's Agustin, the workshop manager.
I told you there were snitches.
Where is Agustin?
They took Agustin!
Silence!
They kidnapped Agustin!
I said be quiet.
Everyone back to your cells!
Now, everyone!
Everybody cut yourself!
For the PRA!
So they'll bring him back!
What are you doing?
Agustin! Agustin!
Come on, everyone!
We have a right!
Come on, for the PRA.
Come on, let's go!
For the PRA!
PRA
What the fuck are you doing?
Are you crazy?
Tell them to stop cutting
themselves.
Not until you bring him back.
He was transferred to another
prison. He's not coming back.
Then we want the press
to come in here.
The warden has to authorize that.
- Get him.
- He's not here.
- Call him!
- I'm sick of this shit!
- You'll remember this.
- So will you.
If you don't hurry up.
- Long live the PRA!
- Freedom!
Freedom!
- You okay?
- I'm okay.
You're losing a lot of blood.
A lot of guys have cut themselves.
We can't stop now.
I'll bring the press.
But first we treat them.
- First the press.
- Treatment.
The press!
Call the press right now.
Civilian doctors, no military.
Have the Policlinico
send all the nurses they can.
- He said doctors.
- Doctors, right now!
Do I have your word?
Do I have yours?
PRA! PRA! PRA!
No! Stop!
Stop! Stop!
They have to stop.
A doctor!
A doctor, anybody, now!
Manuel.
How are you?
Okay.
They want to talk to someone.
I'm going to read the PRA manifesto.
Please, a few words.
I'll answer your questions
and then read the manifesto.
Did you hurt yourself voluntarily?
What happened?
The injuries were voluntary
in response to a situation
that is unjust and unsustainable.
- How many of you are injured?
- There are approximately 200 of us.
The PRA,
the Prisoner Rights Association,
was created by prisoners
when they became aware
of the unfair conditions
in Spanish prisons.
We believe that,
as the social outcasts we are,
that for having been judged
and sentenced with impunity
by unjust laws
and a discriminatory,
repressive and fascist court system,
we have a right to be granted
general amnesty
in order to participate
in building
a new and more fair social system.
- I wasn't going to come.
- No?
Because I heard on the radio,
otherwise...
PRISONERS HARM THEMSELVES
AT LA MODELO
You're glad I came.
You won't say so,
but I know you are.
- Did you get my letters?
- The lawyer gave them to me.
You're nicer on paper
than in person.
You have dark circles.
I have exams.
I have a job, you know.
I make glasses at an optical shop.
Well, I help...
You're in all the newspapers.
Everyone knows
how things are in there.
They started a support group.
I joined.
They want to do a march
so people won't forget you.
PRO-AMNESTY MARCH
They're having elections soon.
The new politicians will get you
out of here, you'll see.
Look, they gave me stickers.
They let you bring that in here?
- Put it away.
- Why?
We're in a democracy, right?
I can think whatever I want.
You seem happy, Lucia.
- It looks good on you.
- We're changing things.
We're on the right track.
Amnesty, freedom!
Open the prisons!
Open the gates!
Now you're only chasing chickens!
Catch it, Sanchez, damn it!
Over there!
Come on, fat ass!
What does it say?
"Amnesty now."
Watch out, she might get away
from you!
Nice one, fat ass!
The lawyer lady gave me this.
What is it?
She saw I had three charges
from years ago that weren't mine.
She took them off.
Two years less.
That makes only twelve or...
fourteen, I don't remember.
Depends on if they pin
the Lugo thing on me.
Congratulations.
I want you to sign me up
for that union.
The PRA.
I want to get out of here.
You don't have to sign up.
I don't?
Fine, but sign me up.
Even just to see you let me down.
Come in.
What's up, Pino?
Look at that.
You know what it is, right?
The French Eiffel Tour.
Take that and get out.
- You're changing blocks.
- Why?
Why do you think?
You're lucky to get out of here
with both ears.
Snitch.
Leave that, get out.
Can I get dressed?
Out.
Snitch! Snitch!
Son of a bitch!
Come on, you too.
Out!
Everybody listen up!
This is a PRA cell block!
No snitches!
No rape and no robbery!
- Long live the PRA!
- Long live!
JUNE 1977
FIRST DEMOCRATIC ELECTIONS
Carabanchel is doing a riot
in protest. And Valencia too.
To be seen we have to be
on the roof.
They're remodelling on top floor
of the 6th.
We could climb up from there.
We shouldn't let in the 6th block.
Why not?
They're prisoners, just like you
and like me.
Like all of us.
We're all in here unjustly.
We all have the same right
to leave.
That's the PRA.
That's what we're defending, right?
I'm not like them, Boni.
And neither are you.
No?
What are you like, Manuel?
Who are you?
I've never killed anyone.
You know why I'm here?
You've never wondered?
Fifteen minutes.
Hey.
Where are you going, Sandokan?
They're here to see me.
Pino, come in.
Have a seat.
Give me the whiskey, kid. Here.
What do you want?
The phone numbers
of the PRA lawyers.
This block isn't PRA.
We weren't invited.
- I'm inviting you now.
- Why now?
A riot.
The whole prison.
What for?
To get the word out.
For amnesty.
What amnesty?
For everyone.
You keep quiet.
- We need to be heard.
- You too.
Keep quiet, nobody asked you.
I'm no good for meetings,
but I am for this?
How much is that worth?
How much will it cost me?
A lot.
No more business, Marbella.
No more dealing with the blisters.
You want to retire me?
I want to get out of here.
This isn't the first time
we've been through this, Pino.
And you know how these things end.
Homos like these two get out
and you and I stay and get screwed,
paying for everything
and with nothing.
I won't give up what I have,
it's a lot.
You have a family, Marbella.
When was the last time you touched
your wife and children?
This supports my family.
Be careful.
It was Angelito's.
That good-looking kid of yours.
Where did you get that?
The inmate who killed him
sold it to me for a little weed.
Angelito wasn't killed by an inmate.
It was a guard in a robbery.
Not one inmate, two.
Stabbed twice.
In the chest and liver,
from behind.
They were paid to scare him
and they went too far.
Who?
Domingo.
You're lying.
There are thousands of rings
like that one.
Not like that one.
It has two initials engraved.
And a date.
There's nothing here.
Only books, Domingo, sir.
Take the novels.
It's forbidden.
Firemen starting fires.
I'm sorry.
It's okay, I know them by heart.
Damn!
What is it?
You don't smell it?
It's hashish.
A left some inside.
A big chunk.
- Long live Cervantes!
- Long live!
- And Quevedo!
And Goya!
They'll sleep like babies tonight.
Have you got a cigarette?
- And a light?
- You shouldn't smoke, it's bad.
- Being a blister is worse.
- Ruby, Ruby...
Let's go.
Careful, it's hot.
Democrat! Democrat!
He's having an epileptic seizure!
Hey!
Hey, you!
Damn it...
Walk, damn it.
Open the blocks!
Panopticon calling headquarters!
Come on, hurry!
Everyone to the Sixth!
Take this!
Go, go, go!
Come on!
Take that up!
Go, go, go!
Everybody upstairs!
Please come down from the roof
or we'll have to intervene!
Come and get me, gorgeous!
Oil it up, you homo!
If it doesn't fit,
stick it up your ass!
Fuck you!
Fuck off!
Bastards!
- Bitch!
- Shit!
Now!
Bastards!
- Bastards!
- Motherfuckers!
Fuck you, bastards!
AMNESTY
Amnesty!
Freedom!
We're asking for justice!
Only that, justice!
Freedom!
If you come down right now,
we'll forget your infractions.
JULY 1977
Fascists, motherfuckers!
How do we know they won't kidnap us
like they did Agustin?
- That won't happen.
- He's right.
Have you signed anything?
There's no need. You have the press
and you have us.
They only want to negotiate.
That's why you're here, right?
It's what we were hoping for.
I'll go.
Count me in.
Anyone else?
Manuel?
Manuel.
These are my clients,
Julian Bonilla and Manuel Gomez.
Good afternoon.
My clients Julian Bonilla
and Manuel Gomez.
Raise your head.
They need to see you.
There will be no retaliation.
You'll come down peacefully
and you'll be led
to the cell blocks.
We want a judge present
and not one of Franco's.
Why a judge?
To certify what you're saying.
And have the guards handle it.
Not the riot police.
A judge?
- And guards.
- And the riot police.
We want the riot police
out of the prison,
far away from the prisoners.
And the pardon?
They're going to review
the request for amnesty.
When?
- I don't know, but soon.
- You're the Civil Governor.
- You should know.
- The request
has been sent to the government
as it was given to us.
From there...
Manuel Gomez Garcia.
Miguel Pardo Nogales.
Juan Lépez Rodriguez.
Eusebio Ramirez Pozo.
- Name?
- You still don't know my name?
Drop the spike and get in line.
Andrés Catalan Lopez.
Fernando Da Souza Lima.
Juan Heredia Vargas.
- Arturo Quinones...
- That man is not a judge.
I know him, he's not a judge,
he's a cop!
He works undercover in Valencia!
- Are you sure?
- Positive.
I know him.
He's not a judge, he's a cop.
I'll check.
Don't move, stop.
What's going on here?
You guys hold on here!
Manuel Gomez Garcia.
Keep your eyes on the ground.
Don't let them trip you.
And don't stop.
On your feet.
Put your hands there.
Boni.
What?
Come on, let's go.
It's your request to be transferred
to Guadalajara Prison.
It's quiet there,
with very few inmates
and special rules.
You'll be out in a couple of years,
maybe less.
It depends on your behavior.
REQUESTS IMMEDIATE TRANSFER
TO GUADALAJARA PRISON
Freedom, very soon.
Isn't that what you wanted?
You're not like them,
not you or the doctor.
What if I say no?
This is my riot report.
Your name appears too often.
That would add months.
Many.
You shouldn't be sacrificing
yourself for anyone.
They wouldn't do it for you.
All you have to do is sign.
Your friend already has.
You have one night
to think about it.
In your cell.
Tomorrow at roll call, just say yes
and the guard
will escort you to the door,
like any other transfer.
Only you will know
where you're going.
Your things are under my bed.
I didn't know
if you were coming back.
Thanks.
JUMP TO COLOR
I've been in this prison
for four years.
Before I was at El Puerto,
in Cuenca, in Carabanchel.
In many.
And I started in a reformatory.
Twice.
I've spent more time
inside than outside.
And that's a long time.
The best way to bear it
without going crazy
is by isolating yourself.
You wait for them to close
your cell door and say:
"I'm locking you out, you bastards.
Leave me alone.”
You get used to the idea
that you'll never get out.
Or that when you do,
it'll be too late and won't matter.
You don't care.
You don't care about anything.
Until suddenly one day
something happens
that reminds you who you were.
Like your first day here.
With the same fear, the same anger,
and the same hope.
A year ago I would have said
it was easier
to make the world in seven days
than to change prison.
Now I'm convinced it can change.
And that we're going to change it.
Because that's what's fair.
I'm glad you came back, Manuel.
We all are.
Get some rest.
JUMP TO COLOR
Manuel.
You have to get up.
Time for roll call.
You're skinnier.
You okay?
Roll call.
Let's go, Boni.
Be strong, be tough.
Let's go, Boni, chin up.
- We're with you, Boni.
- It's okay, we're behind you.
Long live Boni.
Come on, Boni.
Be strong.
Don't worry, Boni.
- Long live the PRA!
- Long live!
- Let's go, Boni...
- Boot's the man!
Long live!
Roll call is over!
Everybody inside!
Go inside.
They're gifts from the prisoners.
For who?
For you.
It's their way of saying thank you.
What are you doing?
Since I have nothing left,
I can share everything.
That's better, more spacious.
You don't like it?
I guess, I don't know.
It's in fashion, right?
- My roommate Pino would.
- He has good taste.
You see how they move?
The spirals, do you see them?
It's an optical effect.
It you stare at it,
it looks like they're moving.
Look, come closer.
I want to sleep with you.
Do you see it now?
Now I do.
Say it again.
"Optical effect.”
Open it later.
Time's up, let's go.
I didn't do anything!
Where are we going?
I'm sorry.
There's no reason to be sorry.
You're shaking.
I'm cold.
Me too.
El Espinar.
We've crossed half of Spain.
If they inject you with something,
don't resist.
Your muscles will contract
and the pain is sharper.
Just lie there and clear you mind.
And don't step
on the floor of the cell.
You'll get ulcers
from the disinfectant.
Let's go.
Take off your clothes
and toss them on the floor.
Close your eyes
if you don't want to go blind.
Turn around.
Turn.
We're in a democracy.
Son of a bitch!
You're in isolation period.
All prisoners must remain silent.
When you see the light turn on,
stand at the back of the cell
with your arms spread
and your eyes on the floor.
Otherwise the rules will be applied.
Get up! Let's go!
Please.
Let's go.
- What's wrong with him?
- He swallowed three bed springs.
I'm requesting a transfer
to the hospital. He needs surgery.
Talk to a prisoner here, please.
His name is José Pino Expésito.
He's in isolation.
I can't leave here, it's prohibited.
Bring him here.
Or I'll swallow every spring
on the bed.
Hold him up.
There, sit down.
- Why is he like this?
- I don't know.
Must have done it to himself.
He's very violent.
"At 23:00 hours...
Capricorn Colony time...
I left the base
to return to the ship..."
The ambulance is here.
"No human came
to say goodbye.
And suddenly
time stopped...
Time stopped..."
JANUARY 1978
Not so tight, it still hurts.
- You look good.
- Come.
I'll introduce you to the guys
from the PRA.
They wanted to destroy us
and they brought us all together.
Forget the blisters.
The doctor told
the lawyers where we are
and they're scared to death.
They can't touch us.
Come on.
This is Manuel.
- German, PRA Valencia.
- Rafael, PRA Seville.
- Gerardo, from Zamora.
- Francisco, PRA Vigo.
Ignacio, Avila.
THEY'RE JUST CLIPPINGS.
NOTHING DANGEROUS.
PLEASE DON'T RIP THEM UP.
SINCERELY, LUCIA.
KEEP DREAMING
- You got lucky, Valencia.
- Not so good at handball, Manuel.
What a game.
We can't stop
until they listen to us.
What do we do?
We have to keep appearing
on television.
How?
Burn down every prison
in the country.
And not one at a time.
That's useless.
All of them together
at the same time.
Then they'd have to look at us,
like it or not.
Come on, let's go!
Valencia is in flames.
And Sorta too. And Valladolid.
And Carabanchel and El Puerto.
They've named a new director
of Penitentiary Institutions.
A reformist.
He wants to come and speak
to a representative of the PRA.
Watch out.
One, two, three, four, five...
Bastards.
Here he comes.
Carlos Garcia Valdés, Manuel Gomez.
Nice to meet you.
You can wait outside.
I don't need you.
Do you mind?
I want transparency and what I am
doing to be known at all times.
If it bothers you,
I'll tell him to leave.
I don't mind.
Please, sit down.
If your file is correct,
you're 31 years old. Like me.
My birthday was last week.
I'm sure we'll get along.
I ordered coffee and something
to eat in case we go over.
I've read your complaints
and I agree with many of them.
You should know there's nothing
I can do about amnesty.
But I can change the penitentiary
law and I'm going to.
With you. Listening to everything
you have to tell me.
I don't want golden cages.
I want prisons without people
who shouldn't be there.
I'll have you all sent back
to your prisons of origin
very soon. Home.
I trust you.
Do you know how a prison works?
I should.
Everything you're saying
sounds great,
but inside the prisons,
the guards make the rules.
And they won't let you.
Times are changing for everyone.
For them too.
Hey!
Look at their faces.
The party's over.
Inside these doors, we're in charge.
Co-management, they call it.
- A victory.
- Look at that.
Look what we got. Kid...
We even run this ourselves.
Hi.
The senators!
"Crimes of a social character
were the consequence
of penal laws that came
from a political situation
now under review."
Louder.
- "That new situation..."
- Louder!
"That new situation and
all the social and political changes
that have taken place in Spain
since November of 1975
motivate us, as senators,
to submit to the House
the proposal
for the Law of Amnesty."
Amnesty! Amnesty!
- Who is it?
- Manuel.
Come in.
Hold on a second.
Okay.
Damn, what a job.
I've counted it ten times.
Beer sells like hotcakes
in this heat.
Marbella counts it
and puts it away.
But he doesn't keep a dime.
The PRA is sacred.
- What's up, Manuel?
- I want tobacco.
Blonde, give me two packs.
Here.
Now tell me why you're really here.
What's going on, Marbella?
It's Horoscope!
Go away, negro!
I'm not giving you anything!
Marbella, please!
- I swear I'll pay you back.
- No. Beat it, negro.
I have a message for you!
This one is on me.
That guy is a liar and a thief.
This place is filling up with demons
and there's a new drug
that drives them crazy.
What drug?
That black pain in the ass!
- What?
- Marbella, it's me, José Enrique.
Open up, I have a gift for you.
Come in, quickly.
- What is this, José Enrique?
- A gift.
But what is it? I don't know
what it is, I don't understand.
It's the Segovia Aqueduct,
don't you see it?
- The Segovia Aqueduct?
- It's upside down, turn it over.
Oh, okay.
Okay, now it looks just like it.
You're an artist.
- I'll give you two beers.
- That's okay.
It took me forever to make.
But two beers is good.
Or whatever you want.
Where are you going?
You, the box.
Look around.
There's a key somewhere.
Quick, give it to me.
Wait.
Here.
We're even.
Manuel.
It's time.
There was no agreement...
Palacios, it's starting!
In other news,
today the Senate voted on the
proposal for the Law of Amnesty
submitted by Senator
Martin Puente.
None of you
will be ministers forever,
and the prisoners
will some day be released.
We're all
murderers and prostitutes.
It doesn't matter
which culture, society,
class or nation we belong to.
That's right!
Be quiet, damn it!
History runs over ministers
who resist its course.
Finally we must report that,
despite the initial support
during negotiations,
the proposed Law of Pardon
has been rejected,
falling short
of the necessary votes.
You left us hanging!
We should kidnap the blisters!
For the PRA
and burn their homes and cars.
With bombs.
- What for, that never works.
- What do you mean?
We have to continue
the legal battle.
There are still a lot of things
- we can get.
- What have we gotten?
Those in favor of making
peaceful demands,
meet in workshop.
PRA meeting!
Meet in workshop!
Manuel.
I'm going to the meeting.
- Are you coming?
- You go, I'm going upstairs.
AMNESTY - FREEDOM
PRA
Hi.
Sorry, I missed the bus.
How are you?
- Good.
- I brought you reading.
It's a very funny cultural magazine,
with no fear.
Much better than the newspaper.
And this is for Pino.
ALIENS ARE HERE
I think they're all
at the Ministry of Justice.
I'll leave it all for you
in packages.
I also brought rice pudding
and canned food...
- I want you to stop coming.
- What?
I don't want you to come back.
Manuel.
Manuel!
We're doing a hunger strike.
It won't last.
Nobody believes in the PRA.
I do.
Laws won't get us out of here, Pino.
We've lost.
Count me out of the hunger strike.
I said you would let me down
and I wasn't wrong.
Me?
It's your fault I'm here,
Pino, not mine.
You and everyone else, you're scum.
They should leave you
in here to rot.
- You're the same as me.
- Don't point at me.
You come from the same place
and you'll rot in the same place.
Don't point at me.
You don't fool me.
Blacky was right.
You think you're a tourist,
but you're just like everyone else.
A common prisoner.
Nothing more.
Come on.
Go on, prove it to me.
I'm leaving tomorrow.
Yeah, yeah, Juanito.
You're leaving.
I'll pardon you myself.
- I'm leaving tomorrow.
- You, too. And you.
How many pardons do you want?
I've got pardons here for everyone.
You're all pardoned.
You, too. You're the first.
Well, not you.
I'll give you amnesty.
Amnesty and freedom.
End of isolation.
Manuel.
I can't take it anymore.
Get up.
Let's go.
What are you doing?
Eating.
- Is the strike over?
- No.
Why are you eating?
I'm hungry.
Want some?
You should.
You need to get your strength back.
We're going to escape.
PRA?
The PRA is dead.
Go on, eat.
MAY 1978
Where are you two going?
- Check-up.
- I'm his mother.
Migraine.
I'm leaving tomorrow.
- When are you leaving?
- Tomorrow.
It hasn't been used in years.
I'm leaving tomorrow.
The yard.
We have to cover it.
It's six feet further down
and 30 feet horizontally
to the sewer pipe.
From the sewer pipe to the drain
and from the drain to the street.
We have three weeks.
Then the anti-escape experts
come and search everything.
- Think we can make it?
- Yeah, don't worry.
We need people
and electricity.
- From where?
- Below.
From the elevator itself.
Careful, stop.
- It's the subway.
- We have to prop it up.
I haven't heard it this close
for years.
We need to find props.
What's wrong?
Did you see who it was?
And you?
Me neither.
The light, the light!
It's Ruby.
Turn on the light.
What are you doing here?
And you?
- Who told you?
- The same as you.
What, you're not glad to see me?
- Keep quiet.
- I'll make as much noise as I want.
Just try and get rid of me.
I'm shutting the door.
Who do you think
we're escaping with?
A bunch of nuns?
What if they're setting
a trap for us?
- Who?
- The blisters.
Have you got anything to lose?
This isn't a school field trip,
it's an escape.
Nobody wants to stay in here.
I'm locking you out there,
you bastards.
I bring good news.
The government is approving
the Law of Proportions,
which means they're reviewing
sentences for a variety of crimes,
including yours.
Very nice.
What is?
Your suit, I had one just like it.
When is my trial, Arnau?
I don't know yet.
I know it's only a law.
Please, hang on.
How much longer
do I have to hang on, Arnau?
I've been in here for three years,
hanging on.
Nothing will change.
This country is for the kids
of its owners.
Thanks for everything,
Arnau, really. Thank you.
The sewer pipe.
We've reached the sewer pipe.
JUNE 1978
We're next.
Your clothes, for later.
It's my favorite.
Thanks.
It's too small on me, that's why.
Do you know La Ladera?
- Blacky's neighborhood?
- Yeah.
I was from there too.
From the shacks at the top
you could see all of Barcelona.
I liked seeing the city at night.
I bought you this.
You'll need it outside.
Daniel Morales Ruiz.
The new Manuel.
- What will you do when you get out?
- I don't know, leave.
- Where?
- Abroad.
Portugal, France, South America...
I don't know.
- What will you do?
- Install elevators.
I don't know either.
There's time, right? I'm young.
There's nobody there.
Where are they?
Hey, what are you doing here?
Going to the infirmary.
The wall...
Hey, stop!
Open the gate.
- I don't have the keys.
- Open it!
- I can't, I swear.
- You shouldn't be here.
- Want me to cut you?
- Ruby.
I'll take him.
Move, damn it!
Let's go.
Inside.
Come on, let's go!
Stop!
Stay there, don't move!
Don't move!
Two tickets.
Thank you.
I think they let us go.
What does that matter now?
You're free.
LEAP FORWARD TO THE FUTURE
Goodbye, my friend.
Good luck.
OPTICAL SHOP
MONTHS AFTER THE ESCAPE
THE GENERAL PENITENTIARY LAW
WAS APPROVED.
INMATES DID NOT PARTICIPATE
IN WRITING IT.
IN 1978 SPAIN RECORDED
79 PRISON BREAKS,
THE HIGHEST FIGURE IN ITS HISTORY.
175 PRISONERS ESCAPED.
THE PRISONER RIGHTS ASSOCIATION,
OR PRA, DISAPPEARED SOON AFTER.
AMNESTY WAS NEVER GRANTED.